W. A. Croffut Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
W. A. Croffut Papers 1774-1933 (bulk 1880-1915)
MSS17285
Croffut, W. A. (William Augustus), 1835-1915
7,500 items
31 containers
12.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author, editor, and poet. Correspondence, writings, minutes, scrapbooks, printed matter, and miscellaneous items pertaining chiefly to Croffut's publications, activities with the Anti-Imperialist League, and the presidential campaign of 1900. Includes material relating to Ethan Allen Hitchcock, copies of correspondence with Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, wife of Nathaniel Hawthorne, journals of Henry Alfred Robbins, letters of John Quincy Adams and Jefferson Davis, and autograph material.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848--Correspondence.; Boutwell, George S. (George Sewall), 1818-1905--Correspondence.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925--Correspondence.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Corser, Elwood S. (Elwood Spencer), 1835-1903--Correspondence.; Croffut family.; Croffut, Bessie B., 1861-1935--Correspondence.; Croffut, W. A. (William Augustus), 1835-1915.; Croffut, W. A. (William Augustus), 1835-1915. "Now I recollect--souvenirs of the sanctum"; "Lincoln as I saw him." 1943.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924.; Hawthorne, Sophia Peabody, 1809-1871--Correspondence.; Hayes, John William, 1854-1942--Correspondence.; Henderson, John B. (John Brooks), 1826-1913--Correspondence.; Hitchcock, Ethan Allen, 1798-1870.; Hitchcock, Ethan Allen, 1798-1870. Fifty years in camp and field; diary of Major-General Ethan Allen Hitchcock. 1909.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; O'Farrell, Patrick, 1832-1902--Correspondence.; Robbins, Henry Alfred, 1839-1911. Henry Alfred Robbins journals. 1870-1904.; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906--Correspondence.; Shadwell, Bertrand--Correspondence.; Towne, Charles A. (Charles Arnette), 1858-1928--Correspondence.; Van Siclen, George W. (George West), 1840-1903.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; Winslow, Erving, 1839-1922--Correspondence.
Organizations
Anti-Imperialist League (Washington, D.C.); Anti-Imperialist League (Washington, D.C.). Anti-Imperialist League (Washington, D.C.) records. 1899-1908.; United States. Army--Military life.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
Subjects
Afrikaners.; Anti-imperialist movements--United States.; Elections--United States--1900.; Exhibitions--Illinois--Chicago.; Imperialism.; Medicine--Practice--Europe.; Medicine--Practice--History--19th century.; Presidents--United States--Election--1900.; South African War, 1899-1902.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Philippines.
Places
Boston (Mass.)--History.; Europe--Description and travel.; Great Britain--Colonies--Africa.; Philippines--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Colonial question.; United States--Foreign relations--Philippines.; United States--Politics and government--1897-1901.; United States--Territorial expansion.
Occupations
Authors.; Editors.; Poets.
Provenance
The papers of W. A. Croffut, author, editor, and poet, were deposited in the Library of Congress by his wife, Bessie B. Croffut between 1930 and 1934. In 1938 the material was converted to a gift and purchase by the Library.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the papers of Ethan Allen Hitchcock.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of W. A. Croffut are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1835 Born, Redding, Conn.
circa 1854 Reporter, New Haven Palladium
circa 1861 1865 Private, First Minnesota Regiment, during the Civil War, and field reporter for the New York Times
circa 1885 1889 Editor, Washington Post
1888 1894 Executive officer, United States Geological Survey
1899 Organizer and secretary, Anti-Imperialist League President, Liberty League
1893 Wrote opening ode for World's Columbian Exposition, Chicago, Ill.
1900 Campaigned in behalf of William Jennings Bryan for president
1915, Aug. 31 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Augustus Croffut (1835-1915) contain correspondence, journals, scrapbooks, autographs, reference material, printed matter, and drafts of articles, books, and poems, including a significant portion relating to Ethan Allan Hitchcock. The collection spans the period 1774-1933, with the bulk of the material concentrated between 1880 and 1915. The papers are organized into five series: General Correspondence, Business Papers, Ethan Allen Hitchcock File, Anti-Imperialist League, and Miscellany.
The General Correspondence ranges from 1862 to 1933, with the largest part from the period 1880-1915. Correspondence after 1915 is largely that of Croffut's second wife, Bessie B. Croffut. Topics include Croffut's various publications, his activities with the Anti-Imperialist League, and the presidential campaign of 1900. Correspondents include George S. Boutwell, Elwood S. Corser, John William Hayes, John B. Henderson, Patrick O'Farrell, Bertrand Shadwell, Charles A. Towne, George W. Van Siclen, and Erving Winslow, as well prominent figures such as William Jennings Bryan, Samuel Gompers, and Carl Schurz.
The Ethan Allen Hitchcock File contains drafts and copies of Croffut's writings as well as a copy of Hitchcock's memoir that Croffut used for Fifty Years in Field and Camp. This memoir, based on diaries, is not in the Ethan Allen Hitchcock collection in the Manuscript Division. Bessie B. Croffutt, niece of Hitchcock, also made copies of other Hitchcock materials, including correspondence with Sophie Peabody (Mrs. Nathaniel Hawthorne). Also in the collection are an undated letter of John Quincy Adams, a note of Jefferson Davis, numerous autographs, including of James Monroe, copies of George Washington material, and items relating to Joseph Smith Fowler.
Included in the Anti-Imperialist League file are minutes and records of the Washington, D.C., branch, along with other branch and league literature, additional printed matter, and drafts of articles advocating the cause of the Philippines and of the Boers in South Africa. The Miscellany series includes journals of Henry Alfred Robbins containing accounts of his travels in Europe that describe practices on the Continent during the 1870s. Scrapbooks contain newspaper columns and an account of the World's Columbian Exposition of 1893 in Chicago.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
General Correspondence, 1862-1933
Business Papers, 1879-1933
Ethan Allen Hitchcock File, 1813-1868
Anti-Imperialist League
Miscellany, 1774-1910
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1862-1933 (Box 1-3)
  Letters sent and received, including correspondence of Croffut's second wife, Bessie B. Croffut.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1862, 11 Jan.-1900, 20 July (Box 1)
  - 1900, 22 July-1931, 31 Jan. (Box 2)
  - 1930, 3 Feb.-1933, 23 Sept. (Box 3)
  - Undated (Box 3)
  - Fragments (Box 3)
- Business Papers, 1879-1933 (Box 3)
  Bills and receipts.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Bills and receipts, 1879-1933 (Box 3)
- Ethan Allen Hitchcock File, 1813-1868 (Box 4-16)
  Mainly copies of Hitchcock's memoir and related notes and correspondence relating to its publication by Croffut. Also other writings by Croffut and Croffut family members, including drafts, galleys, printed articles and verse, and books of poetry by Croffut.
  - Copies of memoir (Box 4)
    - 1819-1842, 3 Jan. (Box 4)
    - 1842, 6 Jan.-1845, 3 July (Box 5)
    - 1845, 16 July-1850, 31 Jan. (Box 6)
    - 1850, 1 Feb.-1852, 17 Apr. (Box 7)
    - 1852, 18 Apr.-1856, 12 Mar. (Box 8)
    - 1856, 16 Mar.-1867, 7 Mar. (Box 9)
    - 1867, 9 Mar.-1868, 17 Apr. (Box 10)
  - Notes on memoir and biography (Box 10)
  - Copies of Hitchcock's correspondence, 1813-1846 (Box 10)
  - Copies of miscellaneous Hitchcock material (Box 11)
  - Letters to Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne (Box 11)
  - Draft of Hitchcock biography (Box 11)
  - Draft of Hitchcock biography (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous reference notes (Box 12)
  - Draft of "Now I Recollect" (Box 13)
  - Carbon copies of "Now I Recollect" (Box 13)
  - Draft of article on European trip (Box 13)
  - Drafts (Box 14)
    - "Did Shakespeare Do It?" (Box 14)
    - "Before the Camera" (Box 14)
    - Geological Survey article (Box 14)
    - Newspaper columns, 1904 (Box 14)
  - Galley proofs, "American Procession" (Box 14)
  - Drafts of articles and verse by Croffut family (Box 15)
  - Printed articles and verse by Croffut family (Box 15)
  - Books of poetry by Croffut (Box 16)
- Anti-Imperialist League (Box 16-19)
  Official minutes and other records of the league's Washington, D.C., branch, drafts of articles on the Philippines and imperialism, and printed matter relating to the league and to imperialism, South Africa, and the Boers.
  - Official minutes and other records, Washington, D.C., branch (Box 16)
  - Drafts of articles on Philippines and imperialism (Box 16)
  - Printed matter (Box 16)
    - Philippines and imperialism (Box 16)
    - Philippines and imperialism (Box 17)
    - South Africa and Boers (Box 17)
    - Congressional speeches (Box 17)
    - Congressional Record (Box 17)
    - Pamphlets (Box 18)
    - Pamphlets (Box 19)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 19)
- Miscellany, 1774-1910 (Box 20-31)
  Autographs and copies of letters of historical figures, address books, notebooks, journals of Henry Alfred Robbins, scrapbooks, maps, bibliographic data, printed matter, and miscellaneous items.
  - Copies of letters of George Washington and Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna and printed matter, 1774-1850 (Box 20)
  - Autograph book and autographs, including of James Monroe, John Quincy Adams (letter of Apr. 15, no year), and Jefferson Davis (note of 1853), circa 1830-circa 1910 (Box 20)
  - Address books (Box 20)
  - Passports, certificates, and miscellaneous items, 1877-1910 (Box 20)
  - Bibliography cards (Box 20)
  - Herndon, William Henry, letter to Joseph Smith Fowler, 1889 (Box 20)
  - White, Hugh Lawson, regarding election to presidency, 1835 (Box 20)
  - Judge advocate's journal and vouchers and letters of Joseph Smith Fowler, 1862-1867 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Notebooks (Box 20)
    - Notes (Box 21)
    - Printed matter (Box 21)
      - Pamphlets (Box 21)
      - Books (Box 21)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 22)
  - Journals of Henry Alfred Robbins recounting travel in Europe, 1870-1904 (Box 23-24)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 25)
    - A-E (Box 25)
    - F-H (Box 26)
    - I-M (Box 27)
    - N-Q (Box 28)
    - R-T (Box 29)
    - U-World's Columbian Exposition, Chicago, Ill., 1893 (Box 30)
    - Unmarked notebook of Bessie B. Croffut (Box 31)